iac.es 2019-06-05

# Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias - IAC -

## Privacy policy

The **Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias** is the entity responsible for the handling of personal data supplied by users through the Web Headquarters Portal.

In conformity with the guidelines set out in the General Regulation of Data Protection, EU Regulation 2016/679 of the European Parliament, and that of the European Council of 27 April 2016, the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias undertakes to fulfil its secrecy obligations with regard to personal data and to treat them with confidentiality. To that effect it will adopt the necessary procedures to avoid the unauthorized alteration, loss, handling, and access to such data.

This legal notice is applicable solely to the Web Headquarters Portal and does not apply to links to these site, or to links from these site to other websites.

### Gathering of personal data

The Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias may, for the purposes of offering its services, request that personal data be supplied using forms that will be used in the treatment of such data in accordance with the General Regulation of Data Protection, EU Regulation 2016/679 of the European Parliament, and that of the European Council of 27 April 2016.

The Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias may gather the following categories of personal data:

  * Data concerning identity and contact details (including postal and electronic addresses)
  * Identity codes or keys for access to and use of the Portal in the Electronic Headquarters
  * Transactional data, i.e. any operation, movement or consultation involving any of the administrative services or procedures maintained by the user with the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias
  * Socioeconomic or employment data
  * Data concerning legal representation

### Responsibility for data handling

The service responsible for data handling within the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias will depend on the nature of the data concerned.

### Purposes of data handling and its legitimation

No personal data will be gathered by the Web Portal or the Electronic Headquarters without express consent being given. Data supplied by users will be used solely and exclusively for the purposes required for each procedure or activity.

The gathering and handling of personal data have, as their general objective, the provision and improvement of services and the following of administrative procedures associated with the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias or with any other service requested at any time by users, and with the processing and response to consultations from the same.

Each service offered by the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias may have additional purposes, each of them justified, apart from the express consent of users, by reason of the legitimation conferred on the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias by the Laws and Regulations that govern the services offered and their associated procedures.

These additional purposes and their legitimation may be consulted when accessing each and every service and procedure offered by the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias.

### Express consent

Once informed of the type of data needed for providing the associated administrative services and procedures, the handling activities to be performed, their purpose and legitimation, express consent will be obtained in order that the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias may carry out the activities relating to treatment of the personal data provided by users of the said services.

### Addressees, granting, and transfer of data

Generally speaking, the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias is the sole addressee of the data obtained. In no case shall the said data be the object of handling by, or granting to, third parties unless it be with the express consent of those affected in accordance with the stipulations regarding such instances as are established by the regulations in force.

When the service provided or its associated procedure includes legal obligations deriving from the legitimation of handling that require cession or transfer to third parties, such third parties in receipt of the data will be identified and the purpose of the processing activities for which cession was granted will be stated.

The express consent of users will be obtained for such cession and transfer of data. Consent will be requested in a separate and specific manner where the transfer of data is to be international.

### Period of retention of data

The data will be retained for the time necessary for the exercise of the services offered by the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias on the basis of the administrative legislation regarding the apportioning of responsibilities.

### Exercising of rights

Users may at all times exercise their rights with respect to the data supplied for any of the administrative procedures and services. For this purpose, they may send a [request form via this link](https://iac.sede.gob.es/procedimientos/index/categoria/1080) or use any means of communication that includes details of sending and receipt to:

Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias,  
c/ Vía Láctea s/n, E38205  
La Laguna (Tenerife)

They may also contact the [Spanish Data Protection Agency](https://www.aepd.es/), where they will be able to look up further information concerning the obligations and rights relating to the Protection of Personal Data.

### Complaints and claims

In the exercise of their rights, affected persons may present a complaint before the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias if they are dissatisfied with a reply received. More information in [Complaints procedure](https://iac.sede.gob.es/procedimientos/index/categoria/1102).

## Cookies policy

The Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias provides information on the use of cookies in it webpage.

Cookies are files that can download information from your equipment through its webpages. They are tools that play a vital role in providing numerous services in the information society. Among other things, they allow a webpage to store and recover information on the navigation habits of users or their equipment and, depending on the information gathered, may be used to identify users in order to improve the service offered.

### Types of cookies

According to the body managing the domain from which the cookies are sent and how the data obtained are treated, two types of cookies may be distinguished: own and third-party cookies.

There is also a second classification based on the time period during which the cookies are retained on the user's navigator: session and persistent cookies.

Finally, there is a further classification containing five types of cookies, depending on the reason for which the data have been obtained: technical, personalization, analysis, publicity, and behavioural.

### Cookies used on this website

We identify below the cookies that are being used in this portal together with their typology and function. The website of the Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias uses own and third-party cookies:

#### Own cookies

These are session cookies that are installed upon accessing the website. They are temporary, remaining on your navigator until you leave the website. The information obtained is used to analyse patterns of traffic on the website in order properly to offer our services. In the long term this enables us to provide a better experience in order to improve the contents and facilitate their use.

#### Third-party cookies

  * Google Analytics cookies: these are installed on accessing the website. This tool helps us to analyse the owners of websites to help their visitors to interact with their properties. [See information on tma, utmb, utmc, utmz, utmv y utmx](https://developers.google.com/analytics/devguides/collection/analyticsjs/cookie-usage)
  * Google Maps cookies: the cookies of the Google Maps service register the origin of users and permit the counting of the number of visits to the site.

Our website does not control the cookies used by third parties. For more information, see[How Google uses cookies.](https://policies.google.com/technologies/cookies?hl=es)

### Acceptance of our cookies policy

The Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias assumes that you accept our use of cookies. Nevertheless, information on its Cookies Policy is displayed at the top of any page of the portal at the start of each session with the aim of making you aware of the policy.

In the light of this information you may carry out any of the following actions:

  * **Accept cookies:** this caution will not be displayed again after accessing any page of the portal during the present session.
  * **Close:** the caution is hidden on the present page.
  * **Modify your cookies configuration:** Users may configure their navigators to accept or refuse the cookies they receive or to ensure that the navigator advises them when a server wishes to save a cookie. If any cookies are disabled, we cannot guarantee the correct functioning of some of the utilities of the website.

### How to modify the cookie configuration

You may restrict, block, or delete the cookies of the **Instituto de Astrofísica de Canarias** or any other website. Each website operates differently. The "Help" function will show you how to do it.

  * **Internet Explorer** : [Eliminate and administer cookies](https://support.microsoft.com/es-es/help/17442/windows-internet-explorer-delete-manage-cookies "Go to 'Internet           Explorer: Eliminate and administer cookies")
  * **Firefox** : [Delete cookies](https://support.mozilla.org/es/kb/Borrar%20cookies "go to 'Firefox: Delete          cookies', on new window")
  * **Google Chrome** : [Delete, habilitate, and administer cookies](https://support.google.com/chrome/answer/95647?hl=es "Go to 'Google           Chrome: Delete, habilitate, and administer cookies', on new window")
  * **Safari** : [Apple's use of cookies](https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/es/cookies/ "Go to 'Safari: Apple's use of cookies, on new window")

For further information visit the website of the Agencia Española de Protección de Datos which provides assistance to [ configure privacy on social networks, navigators, and mobile operative systems. ](https://www.aepd.es/areas/internet/protege-tu-privacidad.html).

### Updating our cookies policy

This policy is periodically revised to ensure its conformity with legislation, for which reason it may be modified. We recommend that you visit the webpage regularly in order to stay informed of any revision thereof.
